Jai Hind friends.  In today's video, we will
see
which pension scheme we should
choose after the new changes in NPS 2025 so that we can
get maximum returns.  Along with this, we will
see which investment schemes are available for employees of which age group,
which will be good, better, good
i.e. will give return of interest.  Ok?
So in today's video, first of all we will talk
about whom?  What is Auto Active Choice
?  What is the default choice
or what is the scheme?  After that we will
talk about what is EAGC asset class
?  Also, we will talk about the
two new
schemes that have been recently added to Auto Choice.  That
LC75 is aggressive and life cycle
is aggressive.  After the introduction of these two schemes,
how will the government employees
benefit?  Ok?  So,
overall, every word of this video, that is, every
slide, is going to be very important for you people.
Therefore, you
must stay tuned to this video from beginning to end.  After watching this video,
you will not have any doubt regarding scheme preference of NPS.  So first of all
I will show you one i.e. slide.
After showing the slides, it will become a little
clear to you that how can we get
more ROI i.e. rate of interest in NPS.
So first of all
before showing that slide let me
explain to you the EAGC asset class because it is an
important term that comes in the middle of the video.  Let
me explain them to you a little first.
After that we will see
what important thing is there inside that slide
which you people need to know.
Ok?
Look, let me explain a little bit here.
So what is the asset class in NPS?  Ok
?  So in the asset class i.e.
inside NPS there are four types of asset classes i.e. E, A, G and C.
Mainly
see what does E mean?
You can understand the meaning of E here very simply.
Equity.  The meaning of equity is understood, that is,
what will be done with your money in the share market
?  Investment will be made.  Ok
?  A would mean
alternative investment here.
Ok?  Here G stands for
Government Bond
and C stands for Corporate Bond.
Ok?
Now here it must be clear to you that E
means equity.  Equity means share
market.  The money that is invested in the stock market under NPS, i.e.
by fund managers, is
invested in the top 250 companies.   The
money is invested in the top 250 companies in Sussex.
Ok?  If
we talk here about government bonds
i.e. G.  G means Government
Bond, it means that whenever the government
needs money, what is it?   It is the
government that issues bonds.  By
purchasing these bonds,
our fund managers take a fixed return in return.
What do you take?  Get fixed return of
interest.  That means the government
provides them fixed returns.
Therefore this class is considered the safest.
Ok?  Similarly,
what do the business houses do?
That is, they issue corporate bonds.  So
what is it like the way the government issues bonds?  Corporate
houses issue bonds to further their business.
Our fund managers
buy these bonds and what do they get in return
?  A fixed ROI rate of interest
is available.  Ok?  So
what is this class for us?  That means it is safe for
investment.  That means two classes, if
you want safe investment then you
can trust G and C.  Ok?  You
want higher returns but it also carries the same
risk as E and A classes.  Ok
?  So what is E and A class?  It is high risky.
So high also provides you rate of interest.
Ok?  If I
talk about equity here, then
we will see the previous record of equity in the
PDF that is coming soon, you will
see there that equity has given
results ranging from 13 to 18% i.e.
return ROI till now.  Ok?  And the
return of government bonds, i.e.
ROI, is around 8 to 8.5%.
Whereas corporate bonds have a yield of around 9%.
Ok?  So here
you have the EAGC class which you must have understood.
Now I would like to show you a PDF
through which you will be
able to understand it well.  Ok?  Look,
if we have to choose the best scheme, then the first thing we have to
look at is that we have to choose such a scheme in
which
we get higher return of interest i.e. ROI
, higher returns which have
higher CAGR.  So before choosing a scheme, what
we will see is which
asset is giving us the highest
returns.  So by selecting that asset,
i.e. increasing its exposure
within NPS, we can get higher returns
through NPS.  So
what we first see in this video is that
in which asset class are we getting the highest returns?
So which asset class comes first
?  That scheme is E Tier One, that is, a
scheme which invests in equity.
So, first of all, let us
look at the ROI in
equity in the long term. If we talk about
equity in the long term,
what are we seeing, that is, 18 to 18 1/2%
?  A return of 18 1/2% is seen here.
Ok?  So that
means we can easily see a return of up to 18%.  That
means,
in which one can you get the highest return of 12 to 18%
?  Inside Equity.  After that, if
we talk about the class that comes second, it is the
asset class
i.e. corporate bonds.
Inside corporate bonds okay?  So
if we look at corporate bonds, in the long term, there
is a return of up to 8-8-9% which is seen in it.
If we talk about
safe investment, in which our
money is more safe, then in
which can you invest?
Where can you keep your exposure more?
Inside Government Bonds.  Because this
is a government bond, what is it?   It is
secure.  And in this, one gets decent returns in the long term.
Gets safe returns.  How much
percent?  That is, around 8%.  Ok?
So, what I mean to say is that if we
want higher returns then we will have to have
more exposure in equity.  If
we want to make a safe investment, then we will have to keep more exposure in
government securities in government bonds.
Ok?  So now let us
see which is that pension scheme in which
we can have more exposure in equity.
Well, I have already told you that there are
three types of
investment schemes within NPS.  Which ones are those?
Default, Auto and Active Choice.  Ok?  So, out of
these three, which pension
scheme will you choose so that you can get better
ROI.  So for that, let me
first tell you a little about the schemes here,
which come under which
?  Comes under NPS.  Ok?
Look, before moving ahead in the video, if
you like the video then
please like the video once and
share this video with as many friends as possible.
Those employees who are
not aware about scheme preference,
please share this video.  It is
possible that through this video of ours,
those employees may
get benefits worth lakhs of rupees in the future.
So don't forget to like and share the video.
Look, as I
told you in the beginning of the video, there are
three types of schemes in NPS.  Which is the first scheme
among the three types of schemes
?  The default scheme
is .  Default scheme means those
employees who did not
choose any investment scheme.
Neither has he chosen Auto
nor has he chosen Active.
Ok?  So,
which schemes do such employees come under?  They
come under the default scheme.  What happens under this is that the
three PSUs, i.e. pension
fund managers, have an equal share of your total corpus
which is given to them for investment.
So which are those three PSUs that
are PFM?  There is SBI, there
is UTI and apart from that there is LIC.
What is it with these three?  Like 34% of the total corpus was given to SBI.
Gave
33% to UTI.  Gave 33% of LIC to LIC.
What happens to your 100% corpus
?  The division is done.  After that, there
is this pension fund manager.  What do they do
?  Where do you invest 25% within the default scheme
?  Let's do it
inside equity.  And where do the remaining 75% of the
money go?  They do it
within government bonds and corporate bonds.
So this means that all the people who have
not yet chosen their scheme preference.   That
means I have not chosen.
Who is all of them inside?  It is under the default scheme
and this is under the default scheme, that is, around 96% of the
employees are under which scheme?   The
default is within the scheme.  Ok?  So the
data might have gone a little ahead or behind
but I am telling you the data of last year
here.  If we talk about the
next scheme, then
what is there in it that you can understand this much here
that if we want the best i.e. we
want returns or good returns then
we should not choose the default scheme also because
what is there in the default scheme that in which is the
exposure of only 25%?
is within equity.  So if we
want better returns then we will have to
increase our investment in equity and
also increase our risk.  So this means
that brother, i.e. to get higher returns,
even the default scheme is
not good for us.  If I talk about
Active Choice here, then
if any employee chooses Active Choice under Active Choice for government employees, then
where is his entire 100% money
invested?  It is done within government securities.
In this,
your money corpus will be safe but the thing is
that you get less RI ROI i.e. return
of interest.  Ok?
That means the money will be safe inside it.
If you take a little risk then
take the default scheme.  Ok?  If you have a
higher risk appetite
and want better returns under NPS,
then what is the third type of scheme
?  That is an auto scheme.  Ok?  Now let us
look at the auto scheme, that is, there are
mainly four types of schemes for
government employees.
First in that is Life Cycle 25 and then
Moderate 50.  Ok?  Life Cycle 50.  Now
see how your
corpus is invested in this.
So, in that, we first see
within the auto cycle, that is, within auto choice,
life cycle 25, what is the
investment method within it, that till the age of the employee reaches
35 years, that is, till 35 years, till the
age of the employee is 35 years, in which is the
exposure of 25%
kept within it?  That is, it is kept inside equity.
Ok?  What happens after that
?  As an employee
reaches 55, how much does the equity exposure
reduce as per age
?  5% remains.  Ok?  That means, every
year your corpus in equity is the
investment corpus
which will gradually keep decreasing.  What is it
that the life cycle is within 50?
Under this, i.e. for 35 years, i.e.
50% of your corpus
is invested in equity.  When the employee
reaches 55 years, then
his corpus reduces to only 10% equity.
Ok?  If we expect better
returns, if we expect better
NPSC and better market, if our
Indian market continues to do well, then what will happen,
which scheme should we choose,
we are going to see that in the next slide.
Look this year, the new
life cycle or
investment scheme that has been launched in December 2025, both of them are
under Auto Choice, both of them are like this.
That is, what are the two types of
schemes that have been launched
?  One is Life Cycle 75, which means high risk,
sorry, it has been named high, which
means, this year 20, in the past year 2025,
which are the new cycles that have been added in Auto Choice
?  One is life
cycle 75 high an auto choice life cycle
aggressive.  Ok?  Now
what is inside both of them these days?  There is a minor difference.
To understand the difference between this and minor,
when I bring the next video, I will
explain it in detail.  But now let me
explain a little bit to you here.
What happens inside it?  As
the name suggests, LC 75
means for how long will the 75% exposure be
kept in equity?  Will be
kept for 35 years.  After that, as soon as the
employee reaches his age, what will be the question?  It will be 55 years.
So after that,
how much equity exposure will remain?
15% of the total corpus.  Ok?  If we talk about the
life cycle of aggressive life, then
what is there in it is just a little simple
that your age has been increased,
here the apply key is 35, so here it has been made 45,
but the exposure of equity will
remain at 50% till when, till the age of 45,
what happens after the age of 45, like
where will the age of the employee reach, it will reach 55 years,
after that the exposure in
equity will remain at 35%, see here it is decreasing to
15%, here still there is an exposure of 35%
which will remain in what?  That means
equity will remain within equity.  So now
you must have understood simply that if
you want high returns even after 45 years
and you want to take risk
or it is high risky.  Ok?
So which life cycle and
which scheme should you choose?  Auto Choice
Life Cycle Aggressive.  If you think
that no, what will I do till the age of 45, sorry, that is,
till the age of 35, I will
keep my exposure high in equity, then which
one do you have to choose, you can choose Auto Choice Life Cycle
75, okay, after that, then gradually its
exposure i.e. in equity will keep decreasing gradually
and yours i.e. investment will remain
safe at the time of retirement.  Ok?  If
you want to take some risk at the time of retirement, then
which one should you
choose?  You have to choose the aggressive life cycle.
So what I mean to say is that
now you must have understood one thing here.
If you want higher ROI,
higher CAGR or higher returns, then
you will have to choose a scheme
which has high
exposure to equity.  There should be more exposure to equity.
Ok?  If you want to be safe or
secure at the time of retirement, then
you have to choose such a scheme
which has more exposure in government bonds or
government securities.
Ok?  If I
talk here, then look, such employees whose
age is around 25 years, then such employees should
choose 75 Life Cycle 75.  If
an employee is around 40 years of age, then
which scheme should he choose
?  Right now, the life cycle can
choose Aggressive.  But
after watching my video, you should not think
that this is advice for investment.  You must consult
your financial advisor before making any investment.
Ok
?  In today's video, we understood
what are the total three types of schemes in NPS and
how the exposure is kept in equity,
government bonds and
alternative funds i.e. corporate bonds.
Apart from that, we also
looked at what asset classes are and how we
can choose a better pension scheme.  If you
liked the video then do
not forget to like and share the video and do not
forget to subscribe to our channel.
With these words I end this video.  Hail
India.